<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of that which is past since the kings departure from Gouy, to pursue the prince of Parma: euen til the first of May. 1592. The last letters thereof came on the fourth of the same month according to the English computation. with new additions by later letters.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1592</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01157</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11270</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851708</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851708</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16999</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01157)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16999)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1306:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of that which is past since the kings departure from Gouy, to pursue the prince of Parma: euen til the first of May. 1592. The last letters thereof came on the fourth of the same month according to the English computation. with new additions by later letters.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Wolfe, and are to be sold at his shop, ouer against the South-dore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1592.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Variant: does not have "with new additions by later letters." in title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:16999:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of knight on horseback</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16999:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOVRSE OF that which is paſt, ſince the <hi>kings departure from Gouy, to purſue</hi> the prince of Parma: euen til the firſt of May. 1592.</p>
            <p>The laſt letters thereof came on the fourth of the ſame month accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Engliſh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation.</p>
            <p>with new additions by later letters.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Iohn Wolfe, and are to be ſold at his ſhop, ouer againſt the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore of Paules. 1592.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:16999:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16999:2"/>
            <head>A diſcourſe of that vvhich is paſt <hi>ſince the kinges departure from Gouy, to</hi> purſue the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> euen till the firſt of May. 1592. the laſt letters thereof, came on the fourth of the ſame moneth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He king continuing hys enterpriſe to fight with the duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> and of the <hi>Mayne,</hi> and to giue them battell according to the laſt order of his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from Gouy: to the end nothing were forgotten that might draw and force the enemy to come to a battel: the king without any ſoiourning, came in great haſt to lodge in <hi>Netiuille</hi> a league, &amp; one halfe diſtant from <hi>Iuetot,</hi> where part of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ſaid dukes was quartered, &amp; intren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. The duke de Mayne and the Guiſe were there themſelues in perſon with the Caualle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of <hi>Bourgonie,</hi> the which Mounſier. S. <hi>Paule</hi> had brought out of <hi>Champaigne,</hi> and <hi>Vitry</hi> hys
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16999:3"/>owne Cornet. In the meane time that the marſhials of the held were appointing of the quarters, his Maieſtie aduanced forward with a hundred horſes, and fiftie Hargebuſiers a horſebacke, and to the end he might both diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer their intrenchment and iudge by theyr aſſurance in the combat, whether they had ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke inough to defend their lodginges, &amp; to come to a battell, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded in his prefence a skirmiſh, in which Mounſier <hi>de Contenant</hi> then commanding of the enemies troupes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of their village, was taken priſoner and one ſouldier of the ſaid <hi>Vitry</hi> his company: hauing yeelded ſo ſlender a skirmiſh, that the king did iudge by their countenance, the place to be more aſſured of it ſelfe, for the ditches round about it, then in the force that kept it. And hauing appointed the night before that all his armie ſhoulde marche directly the next morning towardes <hi>Yuetot,</hi> his Maieſtie depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the breake of the day, with twentie hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes accompanied with two hundred more, and one hundred hargebuſiers a horſebacke, and hauing placed all them he had brought with him ſo few as they were in ſuch places of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage as ſerued beſt to his purpoſe: his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie would haue procured a skirmiſhe, and ſeeing that among his enimies there was more feare, then will to fight, and that they were in amaze yet the army came, which followed the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16999:3"/>king, his Maieſtie cauſed thoſe that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the village, to be charged ſo hotely, that ours entred pelle melle into the village with the enemies.</p>
            <p>There were 18. or 20. of Vitry his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſlaine, and more then ſhould haue been, if the ennemie had not put the ſire into the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage to hinder our paſſage, further to purſue them. In the meane time Vitry and the yong Lord of <hi>Chaſtres</hi> with their light horſes, put themſelues in battell without the village ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by Mounſier S. <hi>Paule,</hi> and the Caual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liere of <hi>Bourgonie</hi> &amp; <hi>Champaigne.</hi> But they kept the place of their battell ſo cowardly, that as theſe few troupes which the king had brought with him, did approch and charge them, they had rather refuge to their ſpurres and to the quickneſſe of their horſes then to their ſwords or piſtolles. Vitry his horſe was ſlaine at that time vnder him, and ſhould haue beene taken if he had not been diſgaged againe by one of his ſouldiers. The yong Lord of <hi>Chaſtres</hi> was taken priſoner, and thirtie or fortie with him, and as many ſlaine. The reſt ſaued themſelues by their haſtie retyring, which was ſo ſpeedie that <hi>de Guiſe,</hi> and duke <hi>de Mayne,</hi> their horſes were out of breath. They found verie fitly to their purpoſe ſome of their forces that had taken the Alarme in battell aray neere another village intrenched. They ſaued themſelues
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16999:4"/>from a ſmall number who chaſed before them a great number of cowardlie runawaies. The ſcituation of the countreye is ſo cloſe and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantagious to them that are firſte lodged in a place, that the Kinge coulde exploit nothing more that day, but quartered in Iuetot and his infanterie: in the villages where duke <hi>de Maine</hi> and <hi>de Aumale</hi> were lodged before with their troupes, which they abandoned after ſuche a ſort, that they left a great part of their plate &amp; all their dinner behind them to retire to theyr Camp intrenched and fortified where all their Army is lodged.</p>
            <p>The nexte morning, thoſe that were that night in guard told vnto his maieſtie, that euer ſince mydnight they had heard in the Campe the ſound of drummes and Trumpets a horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe, the noiſe of whippes and cartes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great noiſe, as is commonlie accuſtomed in a diſlodging of a campe, but they could not tell which waie the Enimie had taken: whether of <hi>Roan</hi> or elſe of <hi>Newhauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inſomuche that in this incertitude his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie to loſe no more of his araye, that was in a fit place to preuent the vaunt-garde of bothe the waies that the Armie could take: reſolued to keepe his array in a readineſſe, to riſe vppon his firſt commandement, and himſelfe to go in the meane time to diſcouer the truth: whiche he did, and went only accompanied with four
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16999:4"/>of his gentlemen in their doublets.</p>
            <p>His maieſtie vppon the diſcouerie of the truth, tooke a priſoner vpon the head of theyr intrenchment, being a Spaniard of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of <hi>Diego Dauillade,</hi> &amp; hauing kept the Enemy al that daye in an Alarme within their intrenche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, diſcouered the lodginges where his campe ſhould be quartered the next daye, and where to place his artillerie.</p>
            <p>Following this reſolution, the laſt day of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill, his Maieſtie came and lodged in <hi>Variar-ville,</hi> and procured ſome skirmiſhes of horſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the meane while that the reſt of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie was in quartering of themſelues, without any other great exploit doon that day of both parties that is worthy the writing. But betwixt ſix and ſeuen of the clocke in the euening, his maieſtie beeing accompanyed with the Duke <hi>Longeuille</hi> the County ſaint <hi>Paule,</hi> the Marſhall of France, and with eighteene or twenty gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen all in their doublets, going to ſee hys guardes and to diſcouer certeine things known only to himſelfe: ſixe ſcore Engliſhmen pykes and ſhot, vnder the leading of Sir <hi>Roger Willy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams,</hi> beganne a great skirmiſh, which grewe ſo hot, that there were of the enimies about 900 or a thouſand ſhot, aſwell French and Italians, as Spanyards, and foure hundred horſſes, who after many a ſhot beſtowed on both ſides came to charge our pikes, but they were by them ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16999:5"/>valiantlie receyued (Monſier <hi>Biron</hi> being then in place, Monſieur <hi>de Belle-garde</hi> great Eſquire of France, and diuers other Barons, all in their doublets only) that the coronet of Bentiuog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio was ſlaine vpon the place. The Captaine, the Liefetenant and Enſigne, and more then ſitteene or twenty other notable men ſlaine, and ſtript of their braue and riche attire, with their ſcarfes of fauour, beſides the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of men and horſſes that were hurte at that time.</p>
            <p>And being not contented with this, as they ſaw certeine regimentes of foote comming be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the hedges to ſurpriſe them, they ioined with the Flemings that were come to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larme, and making togither about 500. or 600. pikes, and 300. or 400. harquebuſhers, went to charge thoſe that came to ſurpriſe them ſo reſolutelie, that they ſlue about three or foure ſcore of them, and draue the reſte before them into their trenches, without any greater loſſe of the Engliſhmen then ſix men, and twentie hurt.</p>
            <p>It was thought that Friday next a day par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular to the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> for his enterpry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and a feaſt of ſaint Iames, whom the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards hold for their Patron: they would haue had their reuenge, but being contented with their loſſe, without hazzarding themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further, their trenches haue beene their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16999:5"/>place without any ſhew of a deſire of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyeng foorth. Which his maieſtie ſeeing, hath ſet ſuch order in the affaires of his Armie, that victuals are there in great ſtore and abundance and hope will not faile there heereafter.</p>
            <p>Since this victorie, and from the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning forward, his maieſtie will vſe all meanes posſible he can, to drawe his Enemie to a bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, with ſuch a reſolution, not to leaue them before he hath defeated them, which his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties hopes to compaſſe yer it be long, either by a victorie of a battell if they doo accept it, or by neceſſitie which ſhal force them to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don their trenches, which is ſuche alreadie in their Army, that all things are three times dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer then in our Campe.</p>
            <p>And this by the grace of God whoe is the Lord of hoſtes protector of the Kinge, reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of all vſurping powers, in whome at all times the King hath onlie put his truſt &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence.</p>
            <p>Aduertiſement is giuen by letters from the fourth of May, that the duke of <hi>Parma</hi> is great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie diſcontented with the Frenchmen that are with him, ſayeng that they doo betraye him. He is verie ill of his hurt, and hee hath an ague which weakeneth him very much, and forſeth him to keepe his bed: three bones or ſhyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings are drawne out of his wound.</p>
            <p>The Duke <hi>Longeuille</hi> tooke the third of this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16999:6"/>month, manie of their chariots and cartes loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with victuals. Their Frenchmen run dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie away for want of neceſſaries They are not able to tarrie there long. The ſicknes is great in their campe. In the skirmiſh that was vpon the fourth day of May, the horſſe of the yong Prince was ſlaine, and he eſcaped very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſlie and hardly.</p>
            <p>The King ſeeing the Enimies to fortifie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues within a wood, which did lie betwixte him and the troupes but fiue hundred paſes, ioyning vpon their trenches where they might plant ſome ordinance, and foreſeeing the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage that might enſue by it, reſolued by the aduiſe of his Princes, Lords, and chiefeſt cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, to raiſe them from thence by force with a village therevnto belonging, being one of their chiefeſt quarters, and to that effecte it was appointed that all the troups ſhould meet vpon the appointed Rendeuous to ſet vppon that wood in the breake of the daie: but the darkeneſſe of the night hauing beene partelye the cauſe that they were not ſo diligent, it was neere night before al were arriued, which took away all hope to effectuate any thing that day.</p>
            <p>The enemie ſeeing our forces aſſembled, it gaue them occaſion to beleeue that it was vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on intention to enterpriſe ſome exploit vppon them.</p>
            <p>Wherevpon they put themſelues in battell
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16999:6"/>aray, and vſed ſuche diligence in fortifieng of themſelues in the wood, beſides the Ditches and trenches which they had caſt alreadie, that the king was of opinion to haue ſlacked his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe till another time: but ſeeing all his troupes full of courage and boldneſſe, hee re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolued to make a triall of it, cauſing it to bee aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted on ſundry ſides. VVhere the Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, VVallons, French, and Lanceknightes, carried themſelues ſo valiantlie, that the firſte that were of the forlorne hope, forced all the ſaid trenches with a gret fight of pikes of both ſides, forcing the enimie finallye to abandon both the wood and the village, being in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber about two thouſand men, whereof remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned dead vpon the place, more then three hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred Spaniards, with certaine VVallons, and among the reſt ſix or ſeauen Captaines, with their Liefetenant, Collonel de la Bolette, with out loſſe but of three or foure men of the kings and ſeuen or eight hurt.</p>
            <p>The king gaue at the ſame time to Baron <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> fiftie horſſes of thoſe that were with him, conducted by Monſieur le Vedame de Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres, who purſued them that did retire til twen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie paſes from their intrenchement, where all their Armie ſtood in battell, and ſlue yet ſixe or ſeuen ſcore more, with the loſſe onelie of one of ours, and bearing himſelfe ſo forwarde that he was ſlaine euen vppon their trenches.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16999:7"/>Some of our horſſes were ſlaine, and manye hurt.</p>
            <p>After this we remained yet eight houres in battell, to preſent then the combat, where they did vs ſome harme at firſt with their great Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, which they had placed in a place of aduauntage without their trenches, but wee tooke another place where the Cannon could not do vs more harme, and ſo hauing notſtaied for them thus long, and the night to approch, that they made no ſhowe of comming foorth, the king ſent euerie man to his quarter, till o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion were offered to exploit more: hauing ſufficiently ſhewed to the enemy, and that to their loſſe that our Infantrie is better then theirs, whereof they haue had the triall oftentimes, and yeeld that honour vnto our horſemen. I hope that God will fauour vs, as to continue our good ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>Two daies after the king had perforce taken from the enemy the wood that on his ſide did couer him, as is aforeſaid: the enemies finding no great ſafetie in their campe reſolued to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodge, and ſo departed vpon Wedneſday laſt, the ſixth of this moneth before day without ſound of trumpet or drumme, in a rainie and windie weather, which in recompence of the hinderance that is miniſtred to their marche, brought them the commoditie to helpe to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their departure, ſo that the king coulde not be ſo readie to followe them, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16999:7"/>hee did about ſix of the clocke in the morning, with a thouſand or 1200. horſe, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge alſo his armie to come forwarde, ſo that eaſily hee might haue ouertaken them, in caſe they had proſecuted their iourney towardes Roane, as it was likely they did intend: But within one houre after his departure he found them alreadie lodged in a ſtrong place and of aduantage, their taile reaching euen to <hi>Caude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bee,</hi> wherefore he alſo reſolued to lodge that day at Iuetot, and the next day to ſet forward to get afore them toward Roane: but being come to the Rendezuous that he had giuen to his whole armie, he vnderſtoode by ſuch as he had ſent to diſcouer the enemies doinges, that they made no ſemblance to ſtirre: whereupon hee tooke againe his former lodging, from whence he was gone, and made it conuenient. For they imagining him to be paſſed forward, there were ſome of their troupes found mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching to ſeize vppon the ſame lodging, from whence they might afterward haue eaſily eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and could no more haue been entrapped, but ſeeing their way ſtill ſtopped, ſuch as were gone abroad returned. And ſince they haue kept themſelues in their lodgings. Three daies togither by reaſon of the bad raynie wether, the king was driuen to let his army ſoiourne in their trenches, and could do no more but day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly go himſelfe, his coſens, the Marſhals <hi>Biron,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16999:8"/>Aumont</hi> &amp; <hi>Bouillon.</hi> The Baron of <hi>Biron,</hi> marſhal of che campe, and other the captaines to take a view of their feate, and of the waies to come to the enemies campe, to the end vppon the firſt oportunity to march &amp; to ſet vpon them. Then hauing ſeene and well noted all that might be done, the king yeſterday determined to go and giue an onſet.</p>
            <p>This morning hauing brought all footmen neere, and the moſt part of his horſemen, with three peeces of artillerie, who came ſo early to the place appointed, that about eight or nine of the clocke, they ſtrooke into a bottome that made the head of their camp, where were lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cornets of the ordinances of the low countries, and twentie of light horſe, ſeuen of Carabins, and all their rutters, who all were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrown with the ſlaughter of two or three hundred, among others, of ſundrie Captaines, whoſe names as yet wee cannot learne. The booty amounted vnto aboue 150000. crowns. Moſt of their baggage being taken, with almoſt 4000. horſe, ſome of carriage, and ſome of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, with foure Cornets that were wonne. We truſt that God continuing his bleſſinges to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the good and iuſt cauſe, wil ſhortly make an end of the Spaniſh ambition and tyrannie, and graunt happie peace vnto his Maieſtie, and all his good ſubiectes, whereof wee are dayly moſt earneſtly to deſire him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:16999:8"/>By other letters comming at the ſame time that theſe did, and ſignifiyng as much as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is ſet downe, they ſay alſo, that in the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> his campe, that a munition loafe, whiche is of verie blacke bread, and is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the bigneſſe of one of our halfepenny loaues, is there ſold in his campe for two ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges and ſixe pence, and that a pottle of ſpring water, is alſo ſold there for ſeuen pence farthing.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>True newes from the kings Canpe, by the</hi> Kings owne Letters, which came on the 4. of May. 1592.</head>
               <p>On Thurſday laſt at night, there was a great conflict vpon the horſſemen of the Enemye, wherein were taken, as followed:</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Seuen cornets of Launces.</item>
                     <item>Twenty Cornets of lighthorſſes.</item>
                     <item>Seuen Cornets of carbines.</item>
                     <item>All the Switzers put to flight.</item>
                     <item>Almoſt all the cartes burned.</item>
                     <item>Foure thouſand horſſe taken.</item>
                     <item>Three hundred men of Account ſlaine vpon the place.</item>
                     <item>The ſpoiles worth 150000. Crownes.</item>
                     <item>The Duke of Parma deadly ſicke at <hi>Caudebeck.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Three traitors comming to kiſ the K. hanged.</item>
                     <item>The kings wife dead.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Gouernour of Roan hath cauſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16999:9"/>botes to be brought to the duke of Parma being in Caudebeck, vppon which boates the Duke made a bridge, wherevpon he did paſſe ouer the water with his armie, but the Kinge followed him ſo nigh, that he could haue no leizure to breake his bridge, by which means the king followed him ouer.</p>
               <p>There were 500. men of the duke of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maes at Liſleboune, which were charged by the kings men, and were euerie one put to the ſword.</p>
               <p>The Duke cannot retire but by one of theſe three waies: the one, which goeth towardes Roan, the which is very daungerous, becauſe there is about ſeuen miles of very thick wood to paſſe, and a very foule waie beſides.</p>
               <p>Another waie, is going towards <hi>Ponteande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> which is a verie ſtrong and well fortified cittie, garded by the Lord <hi>Lauardin</hi> with two thouſand ſoldiors, beſides the towneſmen.</p>
               <p>And the third way, is going betweene <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teandemer</hi> and <hi>Pontleſueſque:</hi> a waie truly moſt dangerous both for the deepe muds, muche wood, and a great many rude clownes, yet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie valiant which are dwelling towardes that waie.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16999:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
